<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Personal on Daniel Hadley</title>
    <link>/tags/personal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Personal on Daniel Hadley</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>What the Critics Got Wrong About Star Wars</title>
      <link>/statwars/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/statwars/</guid>
      <description>A friend recently emailed a group of us to say that his opinion is indeed backed up by data: Star Wars Episode 3, “Revenge of the Sith”, is better than Episode 6, “Return of the Jedi.”
 Like most right-headed people, I disagree. While I am cautiously optimistic about Episode 7, I have not truly loved a Star Wars movie since the originals. And as it turns out, many of the millions of people on Rotten Tomatoes agree:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The most-viewed non-music YouTube videos</title>
      <link>/youtube/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/youtube/</guid>
      <description>Randal Olson just posted a terrific explanation of the storage significance of Psy’s massive view count along with a chart of the top YouTube videos, which prompted a popular comment from u/promyy: “I’d love to see a chart of most viewed, non-music videos on YouTube.”

 .adslot_1 { max-width: 720px;}     (adsbygoogle = window.adsbygoogle || []).push({});   
I didn’t have a special coding solution for this; Instead, I just went through a list linked from the Wikipedia article and copy-pasted videos that I felt qualified.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Political and Public Opinion of Same-Sex Marriage, by State</title>
      <link>/15-same-sex-marriage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/15-same-sex-marriage/</guid>
      <description>According to polling data, this is a current map of popular support for same-sex marriage:
 It is important to note that this map shows where people say they support same-sex marriage, but each state also contains a significant proportion of voters who are either indifferent or unsure.
Compare that map to this one of political support in congress and the governor’s office:
 As you would expect, political support is correlated to public opinion, but not perfectly.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>