<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>DSSG on Daniel Hadley</title>
    <link>/tags/dssg/</link>
    <description>Recent content in DSSG on Daniel Hadley</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/dssg/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Rayid Ghani on Data Science for Social Good</title>
      <link>/interview-rayid-ghani/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/interview-rayid-ghani/</guid>
      <description>I had a chance to sit down with Rayid Ghani, the Director of the Center for Data Science and Public Policy at the University of Chicago. I have admired Rayid’s work ever since he became the Chief Scientist for the 2012 Barack Obama campaign. His strategic use of analytics set the precedent for a new era of data science in political campaigns. At the time, others were trying to reverse engineer his tactics, which meant he was always one step ahead of the other campaigns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big Data to Solve Big Problems</title>
      <link>/big-data-big-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/big-data-big-problems/</guid>
      <description>In the marketing world, big data is used to answer ostensibly minute questions every day: are computer mouse movements predictive of purchasing? Does an orange background increase user engagement? In every place with Silicon in its name, there are teams of data scientists asking these questions.
In the social sector, by contrast, answering helpful questions is more difficult. For instance, is our program reducing homelessness? How is health spending distributed across the state?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>