<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Language on Daniel Hadley</title>
    <link>/tags/language/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Language on Daniel Hadley</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/language/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Irreversible Things</title>
      <link>/irreversible-things-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/irreversible-things-review/</guid>
      <description>Book Title: Irreversible Things Author: Lisa Van Orman Hadley
I should begin this review with a caveat: I am Lisa’s husband, and make no pretensions to describe her work impartially or devoid of context. To my surprise, the character who resembles me is portrayed sparingly, but more than generously. I have no axe to grind! Instead of hiding my biases, therefore, I will lean in to them a bit, and give a sense of how my reading of Irreversible Things was made richer by the details I know about Lisa and her family.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another Failed Attempt to Find the Op-Ed&#39;s Author with Data Science</title>
      <link>/op-ed-author/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/op-ed-author/</guid>
      <description>Last night as I was dozing off, I had a sudden inclination to try and add to the attempts that have been made to identify the anonymous New York Times op-ed writer. I’ve had some success in the past with machine learning and stylometry. And this is one of the most intriguing authorship questions in years.
By 2:00 am I was convinced the data had singled out Mike Pence. I even started to wonder what the ethical thing to do is when one has hard evidence about the source of text whose author wished to remain anonymous.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Machine Learning to Detect Stylometric Differences Between Nick and Amy in Gone Girl</title>
      <link>/gone-girl-prediction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/gone-girl-prediction/</guid>
      <description>I wanted to see if it was possible to train a model to detect the difference between two fictional authors created by the same novelist based only on the frequency of common stop words, e.g., “the.” It worked: The randomForest model correctly selected Nick 93% of the time and Amy 91%.
Background When I first started using R for data analysis, I was mesmerized by all of the packages and what they made possible.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>